<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="aed_schema.xsd"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="st22PCZ45OYNES7I2IKO73TV327M">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Biographie〈 auf Türsturz und Türrahmen〉</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>converted to XML encodings</resp>
<name ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/173759734">Simon D. Schweitzer</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>edition by</resp>
<name>Renata &amp; Peter Landgrafova &amp; Dils</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>Digitale Ausgabe von Biographie〈 auf Türsturz und Türrahmen〉 nach den <ref target="urn:nbn:de:kobv:b4-opus4-29190">Daten</ref> des <ref target="http://aaew.bbaw.de/tla">TLA-Projekts</ref></edition>
<principal>
<persName>Renata &amp; Peter Landgrafova &amp; Dils</persName>
</principal>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>AED</publisher>
<idno>22PCZ45OYNES7I2IKO73TV327M</idno>
<availability xml:lang="en" status="free">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Metadata and texts are released as Creative Commons, Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 (CC BY-SA 4.0)</licence>
</availability>
<date>2019-11-19</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<msName>Grabfassade</msName>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<msItem>
<title type="modern">Biographie〈 auf Türsturz und Türrahmen〉</title>
<textLang mainLang="egy-egym-Egyp-Egypreg">frühes und klassisches Mittelägyptisch-reguläre Hieroglyphenschrift
</textLang>
</msItem>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc xml:id="tla6RCPLPDXWFEOBKVVAH3MYTXCXI">
<support>
<objectType ref="ths:P33RJ7RXYRHW7FU4BA2BULCCCI">21 = Objekttyp</objectType>
</support>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
</physDesc>
<history>
<origin>
<origDate>
</origDate>
<origPlace ref="ths:EM7EXOH7ONGGFBP3SB3YHS426M">3 = Fundstellen
</origPlace>
</origin>
</history>
<msPart>
<msIdentifier>
</msIdentifier>
</msPart>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<listPrefixDef>
<prefixDef ident="tla" matchPattern="(d+)" replacementPattern="dictionary.xml#l$1"></prefixDef>
</listPrefixDef>
<listPrefixDef>
<prefixDef ident="ths" matchPattern="([wd]+)" replacementPattern="thesaurus.xml"></prefixDef>
</listPrefixDef>
<listPrefixDef>
<prefixDef ident="m" matchPattern="(w+)" replacementPattern="morphologicalFeatures.xml"></prefixDef>
</listPrefixDef>
<listPrefixDef>
<prefixDef ident="src" matchPattern="([wd]+)" replacementPattern="22PCZ45OYNES7I2IKO73TV327M.xml#l$1"></prefixDef>
</listPrefixDef>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="egy-egym-Egyp-Egypreg">frühes und klassisches Mittelägyptisch-reguläre Hieroglyphenschrift
</language>
</langUsage>
<particDesc>
<listPerson type="editorial">
<person>
<persName>Renata & Peter Landgrafova & Dils</persName>
</person>
</listPerson>
</particDesc>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc status="published">
<listChange>
<change>30-e39e2ce254fd9bb69be1ec10c54841e7</change>
</listChange>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<ab>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd27Dyoaqzkijn9KZz99LJTY">Hereditary noble and prince, royal seal-bearer and sole friend (of the king), overseer of the priests of Satet, Mistress of Elephantine, one distinguished in front of Anubis, Sarenput, born of Sat-tjeny, says:</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdzf195IiK0EMrWoVgEdbprQ">O living ones, who are upon the earth, who shall pass along this tomb faring downstream or upstream, as your gods love you, you 〈should〉 praise god for an invocation offering for the ka of the distinguished one, the governor Sarenput, who says:</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd7QRs9Tb2UUSoCOVNqJdG5U">I was a trusted one of the king in the temple,
mouth of Nekhen in the temple of Satet,
the Nekhbite in per-neser, chief of the ka-priests,
Royal seal-bearer and sole friend (of the King),
one over the secrets of the king in the army,
who hears what only a single (man) may hear,
to whom the entire land comes (lit. the complete two lands) when he proceeds in front of the people to the places where the enemies of the king are smitten,
one who enters the heart of the king [in private, while the] nome [governors(?) ...],
one who is over the sealings,
overseer of all duties of the door of the foreign countries consisting of the ornament of the king,
one to whom were reported the $jnw$-gifts of the Medja, consisting of the tribute of the rulers of the foreign countries,
one who spends the night in the god&#039;s booth on the day of the great festival,
one who received presents from the riches that the king gives out in the palace,
chief of praise in the divine barge in front of the god,
one who is over every marvel of the Nubians from the cataract area (lit. who are upon troublesome water).</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd7E2Rm0mIEnbukHKvFAisR8">A trusted one (lit. one who enters hearts) upon the landing place,
great overseer of ships in the palace,
who equips the Two Treasuries,
chief of the cities in Ta-Seti,
the one who sailed and the one who landed were under his inspection,
governor and overseer of priests, Sarenput, who says:</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdzdo42WKZ0R1tuCynxNlUQI">I built a tomb through the favour of the king, after His Majesty exalted me in the land, I being distinguished more than the governors of the nomes.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd1LZvW4vIE4FkWUi7xWyo4g">I restored  the laws of the ancient times, (and) it was caused that I reach the sky in a moment.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd9sRUDQ5QEUSv9Rvvw9Juec">I employed a group of artisans for the work in my tomb, and His Majesty praised me for it greatly and plentifully in the presence of the council of the &quot;Mistress of the Land&quot;, it (the tomb) being equipped with the furnishings of the royal palace, made excellent with respect to every need, filled with ornaments, equipped with provisions, (and) set up according to everything that was assigned to it.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd50gbB6roUsbh5yLCoLLNTo">I was not let to suffer lack in the treasury with respect to what was needed;</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd9LIDCFDw07didRSnTpl3dk">the demand was chosen there and given to me.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd1T1Q9Whyk9TteORsQ6ZrDo">His Majesty caused that I led a pleasant life like every official of his residence.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdzvUhS06o04ksewrIUcnfuY">I was one efficient at the side of his master, one whose excellence exalted his speech.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd6yfr6vEg0MTk5FtuLtVVWM">I was one straightforward in the presence (of the king), free of lies, humble when he sent me (on a mission).</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd3Leyr0YMkTzmIIYE2eM0Bc">I was the second of two and the third one of three in this land.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd9VkPvU6tUqMpwnFtl5zCY4">I gave adoration very greatly, praise until the throat lacked (breath), as I rejoiced that one allowed me to reach the sky.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdx1hNdORIU38vZoh07xLoeA">My head reached heaven, I scratched the bodies of the stars.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd9IWVwT2E0aWj4W3vbgv4ic">I brought joy, shining like a star, and dancing like the stars.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd3i8r2RvO0PEjyAavLpP5bY">My city was in festival, my recruits rejoiced, when one heard (me) dancing there [... ... ...].</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd7sGVG7w6EBFhcQ7fAkRC9Q">The old mixed with the children;</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd8fc5OvVNEzVkLCBiFWOC6g">old and young were in joy.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd1iARufnpkdzt6UmcQNivSY">May the gods who protect (lit. are behind) Elephantine preserve His Majesty for me as king,
may they bring His Majesty to life for me all anew, so that he may repeat for me millions of Sed festivals,
may they give him eternity as king, so that he may sit on the thrones of Horus, truly, truly, as I wish!</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdWck3yag9kxknd9nGpRR26s">I am his trusted servant, who does what his lord wishes.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd11KbmkEXUNYiO9PxorEZMc">The governor, overseer of priests, Sarenput, says:</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdwsXRQ4G0E0msx9jocGB6Cs">I came from my city (and) I descended from my nome, after I had done what my god praises and what all my gods love.</s>
</ab>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>