<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="aed_schema.xsd"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="st6KCMXZ3A3VF4LO5IKPSBIA6P2Q">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Text 223-249</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>converted to XML encodings</resp>
<name ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/173759734">Simon D. Schweitzer</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>edition by</resp>
<name>Renata &amp; Peter Landgrafova &amp; Dils</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>Digitale Ausgabe von Text 223-249 nach den <ref target="urn:nbn:de:kobv:b4-opus4-29190">Daten</ref> des <ref target="http://aaew.bbaw.de/tla">TLA-Projekts</ref></edition>
<principal>
<persName>Renata &amp; Peter Landgrafova &amp; Dils</persName>
</principal>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>AED</publisher>
<idno>6KCMXZ3A3VF4LO5IKPSBIA6P2Q</idno>
<availability xml:lang="en" status="free">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Metadata and texts are released as Creative Commons, Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 (CC BY-SA 4.0)</licence>
</availability>
<date>2019-08-10</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<msName>Great hall, Ostwand, Südhälfte</msName>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<msItem>
<title type="modern">Text 223-249</title>
<textLang mainLang="egy-egym-Egyp-Egypreg">frühes und klassisches Mittelägyptisch-reguläre Hieroglyphenschrift
</textLang>
</msItem>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc xml:id="tlaU5TC42UNIZENPB36PXXGWT4WGQ">
<support>
<objectType ref="ths:HV3JFDDE4NDJ5HTBR7F2QWPHFE">Grab</objectType>
</support>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
</physDesc>
<history>
<origin>
<origDate>
<date type="earliest" datingPoint="ths:EBGTMF7GURDVZDFRV6XQU7OEOE" notBefore="-1962">Sesostris I.</date>
<date type="latest" datingPoint="ths:EBGTMF7GURDVZDFRV6XQU7OEOE" notAfter="-1918">Sesostris I.</date>
</origDate>
<origPlace ref="ths:M7A7SPCUZFHW5CKA7IVEAQKAHA">Assiut
<note>Siut I</note>
</origPlace>
</origin>
</history>
<additional>
<listBibl>
<bibl>- Porter und Moss, Topographical Bibliography, IV, 261 (12-13) [B]
- F.L. Griffith, The Inscriptions of Siût and Dêr Rîfeh, London 1889, 10 und Tf. 4-5 und 21 (Addenda zu Tf. 4-5) [H]
- P. Montet, Les tombeaux de Siout et de Deir Rifeh, in: Kêmi 3, 1930-1935, 45-52 [H]
- C. Obsomer, Sésostris Ier: Étude chronologique et historique du règne (CEA 5), Bruxelles 1995, 570-578 [B,Ü]
- K. Sethe, Urk. VII, 53-62 [H]</bibl>
</listBibl>
</additional>
<msPart>
<msIdentifier>
</msIdentifier>
</msPart>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<listPrefixDef>
<prefixDef ident="tla" matchPattern="(d+)" replacementPattern="dictionary.xml#l$1"></prefixDef>
</listPrefixDef>
<listPrefixDef>
<prefixDef ident="ths" matchPattern="([wd]+)" replacementPattern="thesaurus.xml"></prefixDef>
</listPrefixDef>
<listPrefixDef>
<prefixDef ident="m" matchPattern="(w+)" replacementPattern="morphologicalFeatures.xml"></prefixDef>
</listPrefixDef>
<listPrefixDef>
<prefixDef ident="src" matchPattern="([wd]+)" replacementPattern="6KCMXZ3A3VF4LO5IKPSBIA6P2Q.xml#l$1"></prefixDef>
</listPrefixDef>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="egy-egym-Egyp-Egypreg">frühes und klassisches Mittelägyptisch-reguläre Hieroglyphenschrift
</language>
</langUsage>
<particDesc>
<listPerson type="editorial">
<person>
<persName>Renata & Peter Landgrafova & Dils</persName>
</person>
</listPerson>
</particDesc>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc status="published">
<listChange>
<change>25-e2d8c526dc32681d5708a30140433f5b</change>
</listChange>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<ab>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd0n6wBabl0gwl4WmfYTXACY">Hereditary noble and local prince,
seal-bearer of the king and sole friend (of the king),
true overseer of priests of Wepwawet, Lord of Siut, Djefaihapi, says:</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd1hUvDy51k7KkZUzKVxLaFY">As for any man, any scribe, any knower of things, any small man, any poor man, who cause unrest in this tomb, destroy its writings, or damage its statues, they shall fall to the anger of Thoth, the effective one who is among the gods,</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdWBDwzsDQkXorx26WR6x1HE">they are destined for the knife of the judges and servants of the king who are in the court,</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd4nyIgpZpEmEqIhFON8Lneg">their gods shall not accept their white bread.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd1k9O03Cbkczt5kncOXUILI">However, as for any man, any scribe, any knower of things, any small man, any poor man who shall enter this tomb, who shall see what is in it, who shall protect its writings, who shall honour its statues and who shall say: &quot;An offering which the king gives, a thousand of bread and beer, bulls and birds, a thousand of alabaster vessels and pieces of cloth, a thousand of offerings, a thousand of meals a thousand of every good and pure thing for the ka of the lord of this tomb, local prince, Djefaihapi,&quot; he shall become an old man of his city, one revered of his nome,</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdQzFnXwKEkwRvM1Ky9osQcI">because I was a beneficient dignitary, possessor of virtue, who let millions prosper with his utterance.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd78PrtbkOUsZsQU9HBAE01g">I am one great of the great festive offering.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdxQhAC7IZEPthlXlkmByZT8">I am one great of meals and great of catch, who sustains the hungry one of his nome.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd2jSBjEFnkVHuq2v5jkpzSw">I am possessor of love, great of charm, one beloved of the clan members of his city.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd5UtgmjIdkWYk7LkN6xcwlY">I am one who drove away arrogance from the proud one, one who makes silent the loud one, so that he ceases to speak.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd8vFgm4PWUc3i2zWrsCXXUE">I am the whip that chastens thousands of opponents, one charming of his nome, one angry when he sees an ill-doer, lord of sweetness to the one who goes on his way.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd68nmwx1OUhnlxbyhXF2Qk8">I am one who drives off arrogance from the presumptuous, who humiliates the wide-mouthed one (?).</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd82aTqSQlUk4n0Ajuo9zDGQ">I am one who punished robbery in his nome (?), one who expelled greed from his troop.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdQ383FCbekFLkOEL7QzINac">I was a great one, foremost of the great ones, a leader for whom things are done (?), prince and overseer of the priests of Osiris, lord of the west, the noble man of the king whom he loves, leader in the state chapel of Upper Egypt, foremost of place in the administrative palace, great of praise in the Lower Egyptian palace,</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd2IYc3zCr09Pu9Erx3NbT2c">priest of Wepwawet, decorated atop his standard
- Lord of the cushion, one taller than the (other) gods,
one sharp of arrows, lord of Siut,
one who is on the thrones of Re-Atum,
a strong one, mightier than the (other) gods,
one who seized the two lands in triumph,
to whom was given the inheritance of eternity,
Wepwawet of Upper Egypt, the leader of the two lands, the leader of the gods -,
his praised, his beloved, the count Djefaihapi.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd9n2I1V8WUZmo9lJOTiMnk8">The priest of the Great of Powers
- the great god, lord of the crown (of Upper Egypt),
the guardian of the rams/Bas (?) of the gods,
to whom comes that which is and that which is not,
the heir of Geb, his beloved,
the king of Upper and Lower Egypt, Wenennefer, justified -,
his praised, his beloved, the count Djefaihapi.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd1NdNfG7yklfgDDbrLHS3dA">Hereditary noble and local prince, overseer of the priests of Anubis, lord of Ra-qereret (?), Djefaihapi, says:</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdWWkfn1uU0fZq0bTB3QOKdc">I am an active heir, enduring of monuments, an avenger who renews old times.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdx3JgeFrHkCVlsJ4pUNxTyQ">I raised up walls which were destroyed, I covered (?) [..., I found] happiness with the ancestors.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd2q75keWSk33p5a9fwMoMuo">I built the house of (my) father, I renewed every offering of Siut.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd4jUwoHBhkVgop0BkkybWIo">I am one beloved of the king, praised by his god, commander of those in the front, [priest of (?)] the souls of Nekhen,
one who justifies Osiris in his place of the divine cavern which is in Siut,
one who gives directions to the priests as leader of the monthly and half-monthly festivals,
who worshippes 〈the god (?)〉 on the wagy-festival,
who praises him on the day of the festival of Thoth.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd2cYVC5y2E18qdWeKMQguIA">One high of voice when he praises god and honours the souls (or: Ba-power) of the one who leads the Two Lands,
who embellishes the souls of Nekhen,
who clothes the group of jackals, the gods of the following of Horus,
who follow the god to his place, his tomb which is in the cavern of the sacred land under Anubis, the hidden secret of Osiris, the sacred valley of the Lord of life, the hidden secret of the Lord of Abydos.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd3xhkdfTlUXMraBluagyCPk">One of a praising hand when he brings offerings and when he offers cool water and pastries on the offering table of the Lords of Siut.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd8UYZeGOAk2AqWt7cjYDvzw">The hereditary noble and local prince,
overseer of priests of Wepwawet, lord of Siut,
trusted one of Horus, lord of the palace,
one whom he rewarded [in front] of his likes,
one with a hand filled with every valuable thing (and) with food.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd6nUVm1qvEiKtZ8XDUvaZF0">Pillar of Upper Egypt,
overseer of the royal administration,
one stable of praise and great of love,
confidant of the king in every matter of his,</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdWW4Vp8iQUQtudxty2ozgNU">[...] voice [...],
one who subdues wrongdoing (that happened),
one whose excellence brought about his respect,
one unique in confiding to him,
one efficient of heart, excellent of utterances,
one whose excellence was put in the fore,
one revered on account of the excellence of his speech,
one promoted on account of the efficiency of his counsels,
one whom his heart taught to satisfaction,</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdwOhGq547ENQuRnGAbr2UJE">one (of whom) the two lands know that his counsels are excellent,
one whose praise the people are acquainted with,
whose reputation the Lord of the Two Lands created,
one efficient of conduct when he is sent,
possessor of praise under any account.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd5T9XtkOi0J3sOoKh2k4WG0">Overseer of the temple in the sacred place,
one who acts (lit. uses his hand), performing festival in the sacred places,
one who satisfies Horus with his [eye] (?),
who brings completeness (?) in all its names, it being assigned to him as fruit offerings (??),</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdwnExz2PsEsHlQaUvTepjJA">one who clothes the god in his clothes,
one who anoints Maat in Siut,
priest of Isis and Seshat (?),
overseer of the commissions of god&#039;s offerings,
overseer of works, who knows his duty,
one who subdued the enemies of Osiris in the presence Horus who is upon the throne of his father,
the count, overseer of priests, Djefaihapi.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd6KIZVCNm0QTlvci7KzRN9M">one fresh of reeds/sole (?), beloved of his city,
one with a hand filled with every valuable thing (and) with food,
possessor of bulls, rich in goats,
one plentiful of &quot;barley of Lower Egypt&quot;, possessor of cloth,
possessor of a quantity of gifts (?), one known (?) to Upper Egypt, great in all kinds of things,</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd9GULNJznU3dkW0YBOD89JA">whose conduct the king loves, truly a posessor of [...],
one truly known by the king, his beloved,
one efficient of speech in the hall of the officials,
one who finds his right phrase when it is lacking,
one who solves a difficult matter when it happens [at every opportunity (?)],
one sharper than an awn, who judges two peers impartially.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd8OyrFeZo0MTljTEXgvVQVM">I am a member of the council - lying is my abomination -,
a righteous one who has no favourite,
lord of the council hall, who hears excellence, namely, what is beneficial for his city,
the count Djefaihapi, born of [Id]y-[aat].</s>
</ab>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>