<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="aed_schema.xsd"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="stCTKS4E72GVCIPBY2X3PL2JHWHM">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>〈Stele des Wepwawetaa (München Gl. WAF 35)〉</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>converted to XML encodings</resp>
<name ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/173759734">Simon D. Schweitzer</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>edition by</resp>
<name>Renata &amp; Peter Landgrafova &amp; Dils</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>Digitale Ausgabe von 〈Stele des Wepwawetaa (München Gl. WAF 35)〉 nach den <ref target="urn:nbn:de:kobv:b4-opus4-29190">Daten</ref> des <ref target="http://aaew.bbaw.de/tla">TLA-Projekts</ref></edition>
<principal>
<persName>Renata &amp; Peter Landgrafova &amp; Dils</persName>
</principal>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>AED</publisher>
<idno>CTKS4E72GVCIPBY2X3PL2JHWHM</idno>
<availability xml:lang="en" status="free">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Metadata and texts are released as Creative Commons, Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 (CC BY-SA 4.0)</licence>
</availability>
<date>2019-08-10</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository ref="ths:ZN4QSMUSP5FVJBCD6TECD35MCE">Staatliche Sammlung Ägyptischer Kunst</repository>
<idno>GL WAF 35</idno>
<altIdentifier>
<idno></idno>
<note>Die Stele ist im Zuge der Zusammenführung der ägyptischen Sammlungen in München nach dem Zweiten Weltkrieg von der Glyptothek in die Staatliche Sammlung Ägyptischer Kunst überführt worden, sie behält aber die Inventarummer bei, die sie nach dem Ende des Königreichs der Familie Wittelsbach in Bayern bekommen hat.

A. Grimm schreibt in einer E-Mail vom 05.11.2010 an die Leipziger Arbeitsstelle zur Nummerierung:
(1.) Gl. W.A.F. 35 (also mit Punktierung) ist die historische Numerierung, also nicht falsch; heute wird auch vom Wittelsbacher Ausgleichs-Fond selbst: Gl. WAF mit folgender Nummer vorgezogen.
(2.) Im nachweislich ältesten Numerierungssystem im &quot;Aegyptischen Saal&quot; der Glyptothek trägt die Stele die Nr. 27 (also die von Sethe angegebene Nr.!); siehe dazu: Franz Joseph Lauth, Erklärendes Verzeichnis ..., München 1865, S. 43, Nr. 27 - Lauth schreibt dazu auf S. 3: &quot;Ich behalte die Numerirung bei, welche sowohl in dem Katalog, als an den einzelnen Denkmälern beliebt worden ist.&quot; Durch Zuwachs an und durch Umstellung von Objekten im &quot;Aegyptischen Saal&quot; hat dann diese Stele die Nr. 40 erhalten, und so auch nun korrekt bei Furtwängler, Wolters und Dyroff/Pörtner; es handelt sich also bei den Nummern 27 und 40 um Aufstellungsnummern, nicht um Inventarnummern! Brugsch&#039; Nummer 61 ist mir allerdings noch rätselhaft.</note>
</altIdentifier>
<msName>Stele des Wepwawetaa (München Gl. WAF 35)</msName>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<msItem>
<title type="modern">〈Stele des Wepwawetaa (München Gl. WAF 35)〉</title>
<textLang mainLang="egy-egym-Egyp-Egypreg">frühes und klassisches Mittelägyptisch-reguläre Hieroglyphenschrift
</textLang>
</msItem>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc xml:id="tlaOT4KIZ6QIJER7AWP6OU7SHENDA">
<support>
<objectType ref="ths:LCPWQCZ2HVFBVFJHVYSQ2UJHIY">rundbogige Stele</objectType>
<note>1,365 x 0,70 m (Höhe x Breite)</note>
</support>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
</physDesc>
<history>
<origin>
<origDate>
<date type="earliest" datingPoint="ths:CHLJ7SQNMVF33JVUBIZTIYH5PQ" notBefore="-1917">Amenemhet II.</date>
<date type="latest" datingPoint="ths:CHLJ7SQNMVF33JVUBIZTIYH5PQ" notAfter="-1883">Amenemhet II.</date>
<note>Die Stele datiert aus Jahr x+3 von Amenemhet II. Stele Leiden V4 des gleichen Wepwawetaa hat eine Doppeldatierung Jahr 44 Sesostris&#039; I. und Jahr 2 Amenemhats II.</note>
</origDate>
<origPlace ref="ths:UGEDNM7L25CZ5EOPKOT4HIZAFY">Abydos
<note>Aus der Sammlung von Ferdinand Michel, Hauptmann à la suite. Aus Abydos wegen stilistischer und inhaltlicher Gründe (Simpson, ANOC 20.2)</note>
</origPlace>
</origin>
</history>
<additional>
<listBibl>
<bibl>- J. Duemichen, Altaegyptische Kalenderinschriften in den Jahren 1863-1865 an Ort und Stelle gesammelt, Leipzig 1866, Tf. XLIII [Handzeichnung]
- H. Brugsch, Thesaurus, 6. Abteilung, Leipzig 1891, 1438-1439 (Nr. c) (nur die Götterliste; Brugsch nenn dies Stele Glyptothek Nr. 61) [H]
- W.E. Crum, in: PSBA 16, 1894, 131 und 134 (non vidi)
- W. Christ (Hg.), Führer durch das K. Antiquarium in München, München 1901, Tf. zu S. 94 [P]
- P. Wolters, Führer durch die Glyptothek König Ludwigs I. zu München, 1923 (= 1935), 10 (Nr. 40) [K]
- K. Dyroff und B. Pörtner, Aegyptische Grabsteine und Denksteine aus süddeutschen Sammlungen. (Band) II: München, Strassburg i.E. 1904, 2-7 (Nr. 3) und Tf. II (Nr. 3 und 3.a = Abklatsch) (nennt es Glyptothek 40) [K,*P]
- K. Sethe, Aegyptische Lesestücke zum Gebrauch im akademischen Unterricht. Texte des Mittleren Reiches, Leipzig 1924, 73-74, Nr. 15.b (nennt die Stele München, Glyptothek 27) [H]
- K. Sethe, Erläuterungen zu den aegyptischen Lesestücken, Leipzig 1927, 109-113 [K]
- H.W. Müller, Die ägyptische Sammlung des Bayerischen Staates, München 1966, Nr. 31 mit Abb. (Nr. Gl. W.A.F. 35) [P]
- H.W. Müller, Staatliche Sammlung ägyptischer Kunst, München 1972, 48-49 (Nr. 35) mit Abb. 21 (Nr. 35: Gl. W.A.F. 35); 2. erweiterte Aufl., München 1976, 63, Nr. 41 [P]
- J. Spiegel, Die Götter von Abydos. Studien zum ägyptischen Synkretismus (GOF IV/1), Wiesbaden 1973,  Tf. Frontispiz und 99 (nennt es München 27) [K]
- W.K. Simpson, The Terrace of the Great God at Abydos: The Offering Chapels of Dynasties 12 and 13 (Publications of the Pennsylvania-Yale Expedition to Egypt, 5), New Haven und Philadelphia 1974, 18, 27 (Nr. 57) und Tf. 30 (Nr. ANOC 20.2) [P]
- D. Wildung, Sesostris und Amenemhat. Ägypten im Mittleren Reich, Fribourg und München 1984, 136, Abb. 117 [P]
- W. Barta, Ein metrisch geformter Stelentext des Mittleren Reiches, in: J. Osing und G. Dreyer, Form und Mass: Beiträge zur Literatur, Sprache und Kunst des alten Ägypten: Festschrift für Gerhard Fecht zum 65. Geburtstag am 6. Februar 1987 (Ägypten und Altes Testament, 12), Wiesbaden 1987, 63-77.
- M. Lichtheim, Ancient Egyptian Autobiographies Chiefly of the Middle Kingdom. A study an an anthology (OBO 84), Freiburg und Göttingen 1988, 77-80, Nr. 32 [Ü]
- Cl. Obsomer, Sesostris Ier. Étude chronologique et historique du régne (Connaisance d&#039;Égypte ancienne, 5), Bruxelles 1995, 563-567, Nr. 40 [Ü,K]
- A. Grimm, Den Hieroglyphen auf der Spur. Särge, Stelen und Gelehrte - und Ludwig van Beethoven, in: Dietmar Willoweit (Hg.), Wissenswelten. Die Bayerische Akademie der Wissenschaften und die wissenschaftlichen Sammlungen in Bayern, München 2009, 234 (Abb.) [P]
- R. Landgrafova, It is My Good Name that You Should Remember, Prague 2011, 162-166 (Nr. 50) [H, Ü]
- https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/c/cb/Stele_Wepwawetaa_Munich.JPG (22.09.2016) [P]</bibl>
</listBibl>
</additional>
<msPart>
<msIdentifier>
<repository ref="ths:ZN4QSMUSP5FVJBCD6TECD35MCE">Staatliche Sammlung Ägyptischer Kunst</repository>
<idno>GL WAF 35</idno>
<altIdentifier>
<idno></idno>
<note>Die Stele ist im Zuge der Zusammenführung der ägyptischen Sammlungen in München nach dem Zweiten Weltkrieg von der Glyptothek in die Staatliche Sammlung Ägyptischer Kunst überführt worden, sie behält aber die Inventarummer bei, die sie nach dem Ende des Königreichs der Familie Wittelsbach in Bayern bekommen hat.

A. Grimm schreibt in einer E-Mail vom 05.11.2010 an die Leipziger Arbeitsstelle zur Nummerierung:
(1.) Gl. W.A.F. 35 (also mit Punktierung) ist die historische Numerierung, also nicht falsch; heute wird auch vom Wittelsbacher Ausgleichs-Fond selbst: Gl. WAF mit folgender Nummer vorgezogen.
(2.) Im nachweislich ältesten Numerierungssystem im &quot;Aegyptischen Saal&quot; der Glyptothek trägt die Stele die Nr. 27 (also die von Sethe angegebene Nr.!); siehe dazu: Franz Joseph Lauth, Erklärendes Verzeichnis ..., München 1865, S. 43, Nr. 27 - Lauth schreibt dazu auf S. 3: &quot;Ich behalte die Numerirung bei, welche sowohl in dem Katalog, als an den einzelnen Denkmälern beliebt worden ist.&quot; Durch Zuwachs an und durch Umstellung von Objekten im &quot;Aegyptischen Saal&quot; hat dann diese Stele die Nr. 40 erhalten, und so auch nun korrekt bei Furtwängler, Wolters und Dyroff/Pörtner; es handelt sich also bei den Nummern 27 und 40 um Aufstellungsnummern, nicht um Inventarnummern! Brugsch&#039; Nummer 61 ist mir allerdings noch rätselhaft.</note>
</altIdentifier>
</msIdentifier>
</msPart>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<listPrefixDef>
<prefixDef ident="tla" matchPattern="(d+)" replacementPattern="dictionary.xml#l$1"></prefixDef>
</listPrefixDef>
<listPrefixDef>
<prefixDef ident="ths" matchPattern="([wd]+)" replacementPattern="thesaurus.xml"></prefixDef>
</listPrefixDef>
<listPrefixDef>
<prefixDef ident="m" matchPattern="(w+)" replacementPattern="morphologicalFeatures.xml"></prefixDef>
</listPrefixDef>
<listPrefixDef>
<prefixDef ident="src" matchPattern="([wd]+)" replacementPattern="CTKS4E72GVCIPBY2X3PL2JHWHM.xml#l$1"></prefixDef>
</listPrefixDef>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="egy-egym-Egyp-Egypreg">frühes und klassisches Mittelägyptisch-reguläre Hieroglyphenschrift
</language>
</langUsage>
<particDesc>
<listPerson type="editorial">
<person>
<persName>Renata & Peter Landgrafova & Dils</persName>
</person>
</listPerson>
</particDesc>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc status="published">
<listChange>
<change>27-449df499b228edcad64cbd3c5c143956</change>
</listChange>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<ab>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd3t2QLyJUkcRlgGD6vyLPlU">Year x+3 under the Majesty of King of Upper and Lower Egypt 𓍹Nebukaure𓍺, given life eternally.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd0bfPTdGpkNhkcSN05c7KQo">An offering which the king gives (to) Osiris, lord of Djedu, Khentamenti, great god, lord of Abydos,
so that he may give an invocation offering of bread and beer, bulls and birds, alabaster and linen, all good and pure things,
bread rations, Khamet-beer, special (?) milk, butchered bulls, incense on the flame, fowl, offerings, provisions, choice meat pieces, sweets, milk of the heavenly cow,
what comes forth while libating on the great altar,
the food offerings of the temple, laden on the noble offering table in the presence of Khentamentiu
on the Wag festival, on the Thot festival, on the Haker festival, on the first procession, on the great procession, on the opening of the year, the boat journey of the god, on the burning festival, on the first day of the year festival, on the monthly festival and the half-monthly festival, on the festival of Sokar and the Sadj festival, on the procession of Min, on the resting festival of Peqer, on the numbering festival, on the festival of the five epagomenal days, on the festival of the temple of Osiris, on which the Akhu like to eat,
to the Ka of the count and overseer of the priests Wepwawetaa, he says:</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd3akp6BdEksDpA2tU9IfmxI">O counts, inspectors of the priests, chamberlains, may you say:
a thousand of bread and beer, bulls and fowl, alabaster and linen
for the temple of Re, Khentamenti, Wepwawet, Shu, Tefnut, Thot, Khnum, Sokar, Hemen, Geb, Nut, Min, Onuris, Amun, Ptah, Khemy, Southern and Northern Horus, Wengyt, the Ennead, Neith, Heket, Hathor, Anubis, Isis, Nephthys and Sebyt,
to the ka of the count and overseer of priests, Wepwawetaa, great chamberlain in Abydos, foremost of offices in the temple, perfect in affairs in the house of his lord, sole pillar, teacher of righteous conduct, who slaughters in the temple in the course of every day, overseer of priests, Wepwawetaa.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd28eSSvJXUmLikAGgrTte5s">May hands be extended to him with offerings in the presence of the great god, after his ka had satisfied itself therewith.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd271fanEAETUrB7Kgy759UI">May the great ones of Djedu and the entourage who are in Abydos glorify him.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd7oLoRYDsEnSqSGGzQeoU1Y">May he open the roads that he likes, in peace, in peace!</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd3g76upqOk8FmWDpM0SQabQ">May those who are in Thinis exalt him, the wab-priests of the great god.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd0HNAwAVmU1lrKH8SMCn0YM">May hands be given to him in the neshmet barque on the ways of the west.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdWOCxYwodk2Krh2fxoNrR1w">May he steer the oar in the night-barque, may he fare in the day-barque.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdwjw6ncYa0h6sOUwO1utWNY">May he travel togehter with the great god in the god&#039;s journey to the opening of Peqer, the great neshmet barque on its course, on the festivals of the necropolis.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd8FmAStzHUbSmrk2mAyRbqM">May the bull of the west exalt him, when 〈he〉 joins him at his oars.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdyFprLwOs0aXjmiWaiSF7Tc">May he hear jubilation from the mouth of Thinis on the haker-festival in the night of vigil, namely the vigil of the fighting Horus.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd0zMrlrLHkXbseyn8QVELlc">May he traverse the beautiful roads at the entrance to the western horizon.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdz4T2MOL6E4fm4S5VocEPYc">The overseer of priests Wepwawetaa, he says:</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdzJau1KWKkEWu6QrGSWmiQw">When I sailed downstream in order to pay homage at that great residence of His Majesty, the seal-bearers who are in the royal palace and living ones of the portal were watching me being ushered to the palace, and I was made one who enters without being called.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd4IBDUqTD0PAiHgeVQfgMMo">Oxen were slaughtered for my offering meals, legs moved for me.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdx8aqHD1Qk6pkqqMkMIVfAk">As a praised one I came forth from the palace, (for) I was beloved in the palace.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdxt9Mn2aVE63iIqdAxXN8Xo">Offices were conferred to me in the palace, namely: overseer of priests and great chamberlain in Abydos.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdxNTN9sUmkuMnBHTW2PtTy4">My every rank was advanced more than (that of) my forefathers who came to life before.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdyO7Qpt9V0V1pG7GNlXOQlE">His Majesty let me slaughter bulls in the temple of Osiris Khentamentiu in Thinis, (specifically) Abydos, and (income) came to me from their skins, because His Majesty praised me more than any count who existed in it (the temple) since its ancient times.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdyT6qqDxoERDs4dWJHU3jRY">My statues were placed in the temple, as a follower of the great god;</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdWfGLQkbfkdUjzUfS1X4m4Y">meat offerings were etablished for them;</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd1x8RfAXE08BsY1KSckziUI">and their offering cakes were set down in writing.</s>
</ab>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>