<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="aed_schema.xsd"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="stGLCG5C5XVNA3PMRCGRE5WK2Y5Y">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>〈Stele des Tjetji (BM EA 614)〉</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>converted to XML encodings</resp>
<name ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/173759734">Simon D. Schweitzer</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>edition by</resp>
<name>Renata &amp; Peter Landgrafova &amp; Dils</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>Digitale Ausgabe von 〈Stele des Tjetji (BM EA 614)〉 nach den <ref target="urn:nbn:de:kobv:b4-opus4-29190">Daten</ref> des <ref target="http://aaew.bbaw.de/tla">TLA-Projekts</ref></edition>
<principal>
<persName>Renata &amp; Peter Landgrafova &amp; Dils</persName>
</principal>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>AED</publisher>
<idno>GLCG5C5XVNA3PMRCGRE5WK2Y5Y</idno>
<availability xml:lang="en" status="free">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Metadata and texts are released as Creative Commons, Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 (CC BY-SA 4.0)</licence>
</availability>
<date>2019-08-10</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository ref="ths:JMEAGLJDGJHLDJCXGLFGQ6FEFQ">British Museum</repository>
<idno>EA 614</idno>
<msName>Stele des Tjetji (BM EA 614)</msName>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<msItem>
<title type="modern">〈Stele des Tjetji (BM EA 614)〉</title>
<textLang mainLang="egy-egym-Egyp-Egypreg">frühes und klassisches Mittelägyptisch-reguläre Hieroglyphenschrift
</textLang>
</msItem>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc xml:id="tlaPTGKWKQDGVGXVK2QIVQAE2IKOI">
<support>
<objectType ref="ths:CUNICVTWNNF6VN2RUTXZNNN444">rechteckige Stele</objectType>
<note>Höhe 148 cm, Breite 110,5 cm; Kalkstein</note>
</support>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
</physDesc>
<history>
<origin>
<origDate>
<date type="earliest" datingPoint="ths:GQP66JAMPVHVLPQOJF72DRIEGA" notBefore="-2119">Intef II. Wahanch</date>
<date type="latest" datingPoint="ths:GQP66JAMPVHVLPQOJF72DRIEGA" notAfter="-2071">Intef II. Wahanch</date>
</origDate>
<origPlace ref="ths:FYDEOYNWHJEBDHP62FVCZ5PQHY">Dra abu el-Naga
<note>Dra Abu el-Naga als Händlerangabe laut Pier, 159; laut Winlock, in: AJSL 32, 1915, 17, Nr. 7 ist die Herkunft aus der Antef-Nekropole von et-Tarif ziemlich sicher.</note>
</origPlace>
</origin>
</history>
<additional>
<listBibl>
<bibl>- B. Porter und R.L.B. Moss, Topographical Bibliography of Ancient Egyptian Hieroglyphic Texts, Reliefs, and Paintings. I. The Theban Necropolis. Part 2. Royal Tombs and Smaller Cemeteries, 2. Edition, Oxford 1964, 596 [B]

- G.C. Pier, A New Historical Stela of the Intefs, in: AJSL 21, 1905, 159-162 mit Strichzeichnungen Fig. 3-6 [H]
- J.H. Breasted, New Light on the History of the Eleventh Dynasty, in: AJSL 21, 1905, 163-166 [Ü]
- J.H. Breasted, Ancient Records of Egypt, Vol. 1. The First through the Seventeenth Dynasties, Chicago 1906, 201-203, § 423A-G [Ü]
- E.A.W. Budge, A Guide to the Egyptian Collections in the British Museum, London 1909, 68 und Tf. IV [P]
- E.A. Wallis Budge (Hg.), Hieroglyphic Texts from Egyptian Stelae, &amp;c., in the British Museum. Part 1, London 1911, 16 und Tf. XLIX-L, Nr. 100 [Strichzeichnung]
- E.A. Wallis Budge, Egyptian Sculptures in the British Museum, London 1914, 9 und Tf. VIII [*P]
- E.A.W. Budge, By Nile and Tigris, Bd. II, London 1920, 363-364, Photo gegenüber von S. 363 [P]
- A.M. Blackman, The Stele of Thethi, Brit. Mus. No. 614, in: JEA 17, 1931, 55-61 und Tf. VIII [P,Ü,K]
- J.J. Clère und J. Vandier, Textes de la Première Période Intermédiaire et de la XIème Dynastie (BiAeg X), Bruxelles 1948, 15-17, Nr. 20 [*F]
- W. Schenkel, Memphis - Herakleopolis - Theben (ÄgAbh 12), Wiesbaden 1965, 103-107, Nr. 75 [Ü]
- M. Lichtheim, Ancient Egyptian Literature. Vol. I: The Old and Middle Kingdoms, Berkeley/Los Angeles/London 1975, 90-93 [Ü]
- T.G.H. James und W.V. Davies, Egyptian Sculpture, London 1983, 1 und 25, Abb. 23 [P]
- M. Lichtheim, Ancient Egyptian Autobiographies chiefly of the Middle Kingdom (OBO 84), Freiburg und Göttingen 1988, 46-48 und Tf. II, Nr. 19 [P,Ü]
- G. Robins, The Art of Ancient Egypt, London 1997, 86, Abb. 85 [P]
- E. Russmann (Hg.), Eternal Egypt. Masterworks of Ancient Art from the British Museum, London und New York 2001, 82-83, Nr. 13 [P,K]
- http://www.britishmuseum.org/research/search_the_collection_database/search_object_details.aspx?objectid=119629&amp;partid=1&amp;searchText=painting&amp;fromDate=8000&amp;fromADBC=bc&amp;toDate=2000&amp;toADBC=ad&amp;titleSubject=on&amp;numpages=10&amp;images=on&amp;orig=%2Fresearch%2Fsearch_the_collection_database.aspx&amp;currentPage=4 (29.06.2011) [P,K,B]
- R. Landgrafova, It is My Good Name that You Should Remember, Prague 2011, 10-15 (Nr. 5) [H, Ü]
- A. Oppenheim u.a. (Hgg.), Ancient Egypt Transformed. The Middle Kingdom, New Haven / London 2015, 42-43, Nr. 1 [P,K]</bibl>
</listBibl>
</additional>
<msPart>
<msIdentifier>
<repository ref="ths:JMEAGLJDGJHLDJCXGLFGQ6FEFQ">British Museum</repository>
<idno>EA 614</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msPart>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<listPrefixDef>
<prefixDef ident="tla" matchPattern="(d+)" replacementPattern="dictionary.xml#l$1"></prefixDef>
</listPrefixDef>
<listPrefixDef>
<prefixDef ident="ths" matchPattern="([wd]+)" replacementPattern="thesaurus.xml"></prefixDef>
</listPrefixDef>
<listPrefixDef>
<prefixDef ident="m" matchPattern="(w+)" replacementPattern="morphologicalFeatures.xml"></prefixDef>
</listPrefixDef>
<listPrefixDef>
<prefixDef ident="src" matchPattern="([wd]+)" replacementPattern="GLCG5C5XVNA3PMRCGRE5WK2Y5Y.xml#l$1"></prefixDef>
</listPrefixDef>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="egy-egym-Egyp-Egypreg">frühes und klassisches Mittelägyptisch-reguläre Hieroglyphenschrift
</language>
</langUsage>
<particDesc>
<listPerson type="editorial">
<person>
<persName>Renata & Peter Landgrafova & Dils</persName>
</person>
</listPerson>
</particDesc>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc status="published">
<listChange>
<change>15-c134836a084b6b428e1c3e43bd4c57e8</change>
</listChange>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<ab>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd9kVvBVJDEWwilklib1buW4">Horus Wahankh, King of Upper and Lower Egypt, 𓍹son of Re, Antef𓍺, born 〈of〉 Neferu, living like Re forever.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdwPB1y2WAUZDnzDhzEW5WHY">His true and trusted servant, one foremost of place in the house of his lord, an official great of his heart, one who knew the wish of his lord, who followed him on each journey of his, one unique in the heart of his [Majesty] in true being, one at the head of the great ones of the royal palace, foremost of the seal (or: sealed things) of the secret place which his lord hid from the great ones, one who pleased the heart of Horus with what he loved, a trusted one of his lord, his beloved, overseer of sealed things - the choicest ones of the secret place which his lord loves -, chief treasurer, royal chamberlain, the dignified Tjetji, who says:</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd9Nk6b8H6EjamgKY25XCYP8">I am one beloved of his lord, his praised one in the course of every day.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd8o6hNvjQEBXqZ4oFL2cesA">I spent a period long of years under the majesty of (my) lord, Horus Wahankh, King of Upper and Lower Egypt, 𓍹son of Re, Intef𓍺,</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd8j876RcLE2WqaZOZEcq1sM">when this land was under his care, southward to Elephantine and ending at Thinis in the Thinite nome,</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd1W55p8A0UCamJfs14QUgn8">I being his personal servant, his chamberlain in true being.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd2eEv9X0GU20piJlQ1eeOfE">He made me great, he promoted me, he placed me to the place of his heart&#039;s desire in his palace of solitude.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd7drsOO4u0fgjVYESsxtKZw">The treasury was in my hand and under my seal, consisting of the choicest of all good things which were brought to the majesty of my lord from Upper and Lower Egypt, of every matter pleasing the heart, as a tribute of this entire land for the fear of him throughout this land, (and) which were brought to the majesty of my lord from the rulers and chieftains of the desert because of the fear of him pervading the foreign countries.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdz6baNJRk06bqCBSjwEqUpw">Thereupon he gave it to me, because he knew my work was excellent.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdxWWmZ6u8EEmn5LW8h5w5LQ">Then I reported on it to him,</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd11h0a8fGkWOgSSZi6U7pIc">and there never happened anything in it (worthy) of punishment, because of my knowing things.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdwqNXULgnEXRlhFDtuiSW1U">I was indeed a truly trusted one of his lord, an official great of his heart, calm-tempered in the house of his lord, one who bent (his) arm among the great ones.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd3KzDGQ2aEIpkjJFy1JOhnA">I did not strive after evil, on account of which people are hated.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd5w4vBCcQkWyhXjt2xQuYCE">I am one who loves good and hates evil (lit.: I am a as-he-loves-good-he-hates-evil), a character beloved in the house of his lord, one who does every business in accordance with adhering to the wishes (lit. heart) of my lord.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd5TehQQV4kHajTl4T1jWY5s">As for every action that he commanded me to attend to, be it presenting the case of a petitioner, be it attending to the word/plea of a needy man, I carried it out truly.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd68zb2OckEA4jItT5FSztzk">I did not mismanage (lit. damage) the accounting that he ordered to me.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdzAArIExQUNvivMmZrWGdlY">I did not place one (thing) in place of another.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdyPEiXcWsU1UkEZU0drWPiQ">I was not arrogant on account of my being powerful.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd4rudDcP2UBNnyGgCSpdnXI">I did not seize a thing in an evil way so as to conduct any matter whatsoever.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd7K8QbBwEUTcuW0xZVH49m8">As for any private apartment of the king, which the Majesty of my lord assigned to me, and for which he made me carry out a commission according to everything that his ka desired, I did it for him, I improved all their affairs.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd8OaT8vGa0RhjtqWyfApQQo">There never happened anything (bad) in it, because of my knowing things.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd3CkuL0iEUWhvd0tIljZ9sA">I constructed a barque for my city, a boat for every procession: the counting with the great ones, (and) every occasion of leading or dispatching.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdwRtHu2ZO0CBvFibrkHydHE">I was noble, I was great, I equipped myself with my own things which the Majesty of my lord gave to me because he loved me - Horus Wahankh, King of Upper and Lower Egypt, 𓍹son of Re, Antef𓍺, living like Re for ever -, until he departed in peace to his horizon.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd2YgF7t5K0n2majTxnIlyPk">Then, when his son assumed (lit. descended to) his place - Horus Nakht-neb-tep-nefer, King of Upper and Lower Egypt, 𓍹son of Re, Intef𓍺, born 〈of〉 Neferu, living for ever like Re, I followed him to all his beautiful places of pleasing the heart.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd2oSK9kerErPku47BOKbc8s">Never did he reproach anything therein, because of my knowing things.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd3cIj7Jyn0T8ldyGQh7eJMU">He assigned to me every business which was in my hand at the time of his father, so that it could continue (lit. because of its continuation) under His Majesty.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd7WyNV1nd0bRkMJmT9pKs3M">There came no (bad) thing in it.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd1TXQe2aFUZyiY4qV0tzM6I">I spent my entire lifetime on earth as the king&#039;s personal chamberlain.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdxsmPBlFNUSYpeOcQw5R3as">I became strong and great under his Majesty.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd2Qi28fv9UEBvIs70iH2kus">I was one who performed his character (i.e. made his reputation?), one praised by his lord in the course of [every day].</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd9Mll6WbMkr1lvoSS7IHmwI">An offering which the king gives (and) Osiris, Lord of Busiris, (and) Khentamenti, Lord of Abydos in all his places:</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdySqlf3nUUKXhE4iOqlk7ME">an invocation offering of a thousand of bread and beer, a thousand of bulls and fowl, a thousand of alabaster and linen, a thousand of every good and pure thing, food supply and required offerings, the provisions of the Lord of Abydos, pure bread of the temple of Montu, libations, offerings and food of which the akh-spirits like to eat for the overseer of the treasury and royal chamberlain, the dignified Tjetji.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdxPshe5rkkQXtcrRCc9bncU">May he fare the firmament,</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd9wKAkSyr0G3tJCSgyGWCD4">may he travel through the sky.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd2zVca0uOkGDlx4yfT8WZOU">May he ascend to the great god.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd7xm0OEOE0uwvOqvrQ9Cr0c">May he land in peace in the beautiful West.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd1CHR5uIWE56kxWUFwXeea4">May the desert open her arm(s) for him,</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdyoHQ4jUHkOgi4E4COp8xFI">may the West lend him her arms.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd1zupJ8PqkMorPT8iDbCuSo">May he reach the council of (the) god.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdzAIqVz9wEEFqVXP1t0tAec">May &quot;welcome&quot; be said to him by the great ones of Abydos.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd2br1dl1D0ysup7hHl4RQuA">May hands be given to him in the neshmet barque on the roads of the West.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd4u6cEYNG0ZxrN5pv8w1awY">May he go, well and in peace, to the horizon, to the place where Osiris is.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd9nAX55HLEpHo9hTIC1kxLc">May he open the roads which he wishes, to the gates which are in the sacred land.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdwI59lKI3EJUsrEZLIlFDrk">May the ones who are in abundance give him their document concerning the district Redit-heteput, while his ka is with him, his offerings in front of him - the dignified Tje[tji].</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd8WIY6wbIEftvrIHTAodBkE">Overseer of the treasury, the dignified Tjetji.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd4hGQSFPOUa2kYgrQukW7CM">His trusted sealer Megegi.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd3kGDkjzGUKhucBKfoUMc7E">His retainer Tjereru.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdyAya6vKjUq6jw6rhILAkzo">Opening of the $mrḥ.t$-oil in front of the dignified Tjetji. Festduft-Öl; Hekenu-Öl; Sefetj-Öl; Nechenem-Öl; Tewaut-Öl; bestes Koniferenöl; (bestes) Libyeröl.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdwqIouG2bU2Vmv3GoSr9iec">An invocation offering for him: may he be given the required offerings, which are provided on the monthly and half-monthly festival and on all festivals - for the ka of the dignified king&#039;s chamberlain, the trusted one of his lord, Tjetj(i).</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdx85BnW4Hk4LkpraMfDs3bY">Ankhi.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd3S64pFIpEfxpShdH4YjsbE">Extending the hand to the very choicest (things) by (or: for?) the ka of the dignified Tjetji.</s>
</ab>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>