<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="aed_schema.xsd"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="stN4UOLPQUSZDHLDRC2GOC4HUPHU">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>〈Stele des Wepwawetaa (Leiden V4 = AP 63)〉</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>converted to XML encodings</resp>
<name ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/173759734">Simon D. Schweitzer</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>edition by</resp>
<name>Renata &amp; Peter Landgrafova &amp; Dils</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>Digitale Ausgabe von 〈Stele des Wepwawetaa (Leiden V4 = AP 63)〉 nach den <ref target="urn:nbn:de:kobv:b4-opus4-29190">Daten</ref> des <ref target="http://aaew.bbaw.de/tla">TLA-Projekts</ref></edition>
<principal>
<persName>Renata &amp; Peter Landgrafova &amp; Dils</persName>
</principal>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>AED</publisher>
<idno>N4UOLPQUSZDHLDRC2GOC4HUPHU</idno>
<availability xml:lang="en" status="free">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Metadata and texts are released as Creative Commons, Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 (CC BY-SA 4.0)</licence>
</availability>
<date>2019-08-10</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository ref="ths:ASJFDNBGLNHCZPUR7AAGPKVNJE">Rijksmuseum van Oudheden</repository>
<idno>V 4</idno>
<msName>Stele des Wepwawetaa (Leiden V4 = AP 63)</msName>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<msItem>
<title type="modern">〈Stele des Wepwawetaa (Leiden V4 = AP 63)〉</title>
<textLang mainLang="egy-egym-Egyp-Egypreg">frühes und klassisches Mittelägyptisch-reguläre Hieroglyphenschrift
</textLang>
<note>Biographie</note>
</msItem>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc xml:id="tlaJYZXOQVHIRF6RLH5VOXI2LAQ5I">
<support>
<objectType ref="ths:EP7XNRXU4ZAU7BKOHF5H2PYC34">Stele</objectType>
<objectType ref="ths:PWGM75NZGRA57OF5OMLBT7LMPI">Hohlkehle + Rundstab</objectType>
<note>1,60 x 1,05 m (Höhe x Breite)</note>
</support>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
</physDesc>
<history>
<origin>
<origDate>
<date type="earliest" datingPoint="ths:EBGTMF7GURDVZDFRV6XQU7OEOE" notBefore="-1962">Sesostris I.</date>
<date type="latest" datingPoint="ths:CHLJ7SQNMVF33JVUBIZTIYH5PQ" notAfter="-1883">Amenemhet II.</date>
<note>Erwähnung von Jahr 44 Sesostris&#039; I. und von Jahr 2 Amenemhets II.</note>
</origDate>
<origPlace ref="ths:UGEDNM7L25CZ5EOPKOT4HIZAFY">Abydos
<note>Angekauft aus der Sammlung Anastasi. Aus Abydos wegen stilistischer und inhaltlicher Gründe (Simpson, ANOC 20.1)</note>
</origPlace>
</origin>
</history>
<additional>
<listBibl>
<bibl>- K. Piehl, Inscriptions hiéroglyphiques recueillies en Europe et en Égypte. Troisième série, Leipzig 1895-1903: Planches, Leipzig 1895, Tf. XX-XXI; Commentaire, Leipzig 1903, 15-17 [H,Ü]
- P.A. Boeser, Beschreibung der aegyptischen Sammlung des Niederländischen Reichsmuseums der Altertümer in Leiden. Die Denkmäler der Zeit zwischen dem Alten und Mittleren Reich und des Mittleren Reiches. Erste Abteilung: Stelen = Beschrijving van de Egyptische verzameling in het Rijksmuseum van Oudheden te Leiden De monumenten van den tijd tusschen het Oude en het Middelrijk en van het Middelrijk, 1. afd., Steles, &#039;s Gravenhage 1909, 3 (Nr. 5) und Tf. IV [*P]
- K. Sethe, Aegyptische Lesestücke zum Gebrauch im akademischen Unterricht. Texte des Mittleren Reiches, Leipzig 1924, 72-73, Nr. 15.a [H]
- K. Sethe, Erläuterungen zu den aegyptischen Lesestücken, Leipzig 1927, 107-109 [K]
- J. Spiegel, Die Götter von Abydos. Studien zum ägyptischen Synkretismus (GOF IV/1), Wiesbaden 1973, 84 und 125-127 [K]
- W.K. Simpson, The Terrace of the Great God at Abydos: The Offering chapels of Dynasties 12 and 13 (Publications of the Pennsylvania-Yale Expedition to Egypt, 5), New Haven and Philadelphia 1974, 18 und Tf. 30 (Nr. ANOC 20.1) [P]
- M. Lichtheim, Ancient Egyptian Autobiographies chiefly of the Middle Kingdom. A study an an anthology (OBO 84), Freiburg und Göttingen 1988, 75-77, Nr. 31 [Ü]
- K. Jansen-Winkeln, &quot;The Career of the Egyptian High Priest Bakenkhons,&quot; in: JNES 52, 1993, 221-225
- Cl. Obsomer, Sesostris Ier. Étude chronologique et historique du régne (Connaisance d&#039;Égypte ancienne, 5), Bruxelles 1995, 138 (Fig. 18) und 535-539, Nr. 31 [Ü,K]
- N. Favry, Le Nomarque sous le règne de Sésostris Ier, Paris 2004, 318-319 [K]
- R. Landgrafova, It is My Good Name that You Should Remember, Prague 2011, 156-160 (Nr. 49) [H, Ü]</bibl>
</listBibl>
</additional>
<msPart>
<msIdentifier>
<repository ref="ths:ASJFDNBGLNHCZPUR7AAGPKVNJE">Rijksmuseum van Oudheden</repository>
<idno>V 4</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msPart>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<listPrefixDef>
<prefixDef ident="tla" matchPattern="(d+)" replacementPattern="dictionary.xml#l$1"></prefixDef>
</listPrefixDef>
<listPrefixDef>
<prefixDef ident="ths" matchPattern="([wd]+)" replacementPattern="thesaurus.xml"></prefixDef>
</listPrefixDef>
<listPrefixDef>
<prefixDef ident="m" matchPattern="(w+)" replacementPattern="morphologicalFeatures.xml"></prefixDef>
</listPrefixDef>
<listPrefixDef>
<prefixDef ident="src" matchPattern="([wd]+)" replacementPattern="N4UOLPQUSZDHLDRC2GOC4HUPHU.xml#l$1"></prefixDef>
</listPrefixDef>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="egy-egym-Egyp-Egypreg">frühes und klassisches Mittelägyptisch-reguläre Hieroglyphenschrift
</language>
</langUsage>
<particDesc>
<listPerson type="editorial">
<person>
<persName>Renata & Peter Landgrafova & Dils</persName>
</person>
</listPerson>
</particDesc>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc status="published">
<listChange>
<change>22-7da645870c16701a572fc6f248071e6d</change>
</listChange>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<ab>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdy65FGro6kbCkT04JHuu1gQ">The Horus Hekenemmaat, Two Ladies Hekenemmaat, (golden) Falcon Maa-kheru-em-neb-[taui, King of Upper and Lower Egypt Nebkaure, son of Re Amen]emhat (= Amenemhat II), given life [eternally], Year 2.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdwDBsfvQv0jWvzuFDUIKwHo">The Horus Ankhmesut, Two Ladies Ankhmesut, King of Upper and Lower Egypt Kheperkare, son of Re Sesostris (= Sesostris I), who lives eternally, Year 44.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdQsBmwcWy016vcTq2P6Q6Q4">Hereditary noble and local prince,
royal seal bearer and sole friend (of the king),
sem-priest, inspector of all aprons,
mouth of Nekhen, priest of Ma&#039;at,
overseer of the equipment which is in the presence of the god,
great wab-priest of Osiris,
overseer of linen in the Great House,
foremost of place in the noble chamber,
chief of secrets of unique seeing,
great chamberlain in Abydos,
master of silence in private,
one with his arm covered in the secret places as one who sees the beauty of his lord,
to whom is entrusted that which is and that which is not on account of his being efficient in the heart (of the king),
hereditary noble and local prince,
overseer of the priests, Wepwawetaa says:</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd7TgfVlhSkyev1RqQIRHieI">As for this tomb, which I made in the desert of the sacred land, in the midst of the/my ancestors who had created my flesh (and of) the dignitaries of the first (primeval) time, the possessors of monuments as ancient office-holders, the primeval ones (?) who started with the making of the sandbank of Heqet since the time of Geb, I built it in order to make lasting my place in their midst in the realm of the dead (lit. nome of silence).</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd5ctLjEQU0iHiOTAnDak5co">I held office (already) when I was in (my) childhood;</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd7j3lEvOZUQ8sNpeAJJSyUg">I became a priest at my time of becoming knowledgeable.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdw08x2qtLUeUlTvNYCsJ8QE">I was diligent under the command of the king;</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdw9p7VQSCkdqm6EZwrLGEJs">I united with the praised ones.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd9GI7b0quUeQr5flIAthzzQ">The king rewarded me as one who comes and grows;</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdyL1P5Mz5k1xgF24I68aoOM">I was born as one who is wise in his doing.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdzsvetoSCE4dppQmSLJcDi4">It was my own heart that advanced my position:</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd81VihAqVUQHmLWRfw05OfA">I surpassed the deeds of my ancestors and I have truly done that which the king loved, my office being renowned in the entire land, love of me being in the body of the sovereign.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd7uSDoHOKEniiTzi0oQoV3s">It was, moreover, the king of Upper and Lower Egypt Kheperkare who placed me in the midst of his officals, because I was efficient in the heart of His Majesty:</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd6jgVnVWXk2jvdONewnEDc4">I entered my house and the house of my father, so that I would be seated on my place in the temple.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd3RMNUZx6ElKpFDC3OGkjBo">I fared down- and upstream from the residence, so that (I) would know.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd04SU6bzyEaQhm3L6iiSAYQ">I did not do more than was said;</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd7w1hxeZokzjsh5LnFSIepc">I did not do evil against people, (for) it is what god hates.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdwWjjAnU7EwFoEaSTs9xEKU">I buried the old one of my city, I provided for the one who was not provided for.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdxxWTWZWOk5OpuYfdwHbyIU">I was a silent one among the officials,
one of whom it was said: &quot;await his arrival!&quot;,
whose heart conducted his affairs,
who was sent on account his being efficient in the heart (of the king),
whom the king honoured in front of the Two Lands,
his trusted one at the fore of his subjects,
a truly rightful one to (lit. in the presence of) people,
an official who untied what was knotted,
one beloved of the gods of Thinis.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdwYWatuO90qKjE8hxWig9c4">An offering which the king gives, and Osiris, lord of Busiris, the great god, lord of Abydos, which Anubis who is atop his mountain, Imiut, lord of the sacred land, gives, and which Heqet together with Khnum give, and the gods of the sandbanks of Hu:</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd8k9eUIHqkHqpW7XJ08zNYM">may they give an invocation offering of a thousand of bulls and fowl, alabaster and 〈clothes〉 on the First Procession, in the Great Procession, on the Wag festival, on the festival of Thot, on the Rekeh festival, on the festival of the first day of the year, on every great festival performed in this temple.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd7zogbEoPEsukzn4elvQLYw">May Mehwen extend his hand to him, at the head of the dignitaries.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdQrbPtayQEKjlEwO6c0Qylw">May Osiris advance my place more than that of the great ones who are in the sacred land, for I am indeed a man for whom the hand is extended.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd5sqH7gCXUZKsMXpEGRBFFs">I am a son of a great official of the Thinite nome, a magnate in his house, one great in his field, one rich in meat-offerings in the temple.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdx6NfEVmKUVWnLOjSTjt13k">My fathers were lords since the ancestors, children and seed of the primeval ones, and officials of the first time.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdzxDwkVfTUyTncM8sy6tS8k">The distinguished one, governor and overseer of priests Wepwawetaa, possessor of distinction.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd5nVskTyHUGuk0WG1vBWS2U">Inspecting the deliveries of the domain by the well-provided hereditary noble and local prince, overseer of priests, Wepwawetaa, possessor of distinction.</s>
</ab>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>