<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="aed_schema.xsd"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="stQDMTBLQIZZBMJGFKLESAITOSEI">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>〈Stele des Ichernofret (Berlin 1204)〉</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>converted to XML encodings</resp>
<name ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/173759734">Simon D. Schweitzer</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>edition by</resp>
<name>Renata &amp; Peter Landgrafova &amp; Dils</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>Digitale Ausgabe von 〈Stele des Ichernofret (Berlin 1204)〉 nach den <ref target="urn:nbn:de:kobv:b4-opus4-29190">Daten</ref> des <ref target="http://aaew.bbaw.de/tla">TLA-Projekts</ref></edition>
<principal>
<persName>Renata &amp; Peter Landgrafova &amp; Dils</persName>
</principal>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>AED</publisher>
<idno>QDMTBLQIZZBMJGFKLESAITOSEI</idno>
<availability xml:lang="en" status="free">
<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Metadata and texts are released as Creative Commons, Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 (CC BY-SA 4.0)</licence>
</availability>
<date>2019-11-19</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository ref="ths:GOUD7BQ5DBCENBWBR4KFWDW5SI">Ägyptisches Museum und Papyrussammlung</repository>
<idno>1204</idno>
<msName>Stele des Ichernofret (Berlin 1204)</msName>
</msIdentifier>
<msContents>
<msItem>
<title type="modern">〈Stele des Ichernofret (Berlin 1204)〉</title>
<textLang mainLang="egy-egym-Egyp-Egypreg">frühes und klassisches Mittelägyptisch-reguläre Hieroglyphenschrift
</textLang>
<note>Biographie</note>
</msItem>
</msContents>
<physDesc>
<objectDesc>
<supportDesc xml:id="tlaKSFTSSWJDRAK3PWC4MFR6LYF2Q">
<support>
<objectType ref="ths:LCPWQCZ2HVFBVFJHVYSQ2UJHIY">rundbogige Stele</objectType>
<note>102 x 65 cm (Höhe x Breite)</note>
</support>
</supportDesc>
</objectDesc>
</physDesc>
<history>
<origin>
<origDate>
<date type="earliest" datingPoint="ths:QGFPPB7TBJC4DOC46YTOAH4UYM" notBefore="-1872">Sesostris III.</date>
<date type="latest" datingPoint="ths:QGFPPB7TBJC4DOC46YTOAH4UYM" notAfter="-1854">Sesostris III.</date>
</origDate>
<origPlace ref="ths:UGEDNM7L25CZ5EOPKOT4HIZAFY">Abydos
<note>1837/38 aus der Sammlung Drovetti erworben. Gehört aus inhaltlichen Gründen nach Abydos.</note>
</origPlace>
</origin>
</history>
<additional>
<listBibl>
<bibl>- Porter und Moss, Topographical Bibliography, V, 97 [B]
- Lepsius, Denkmäler, II, Tf. 135.h [F]
- H. Schäfer, Die Mysterien des Osiris in Abydos unter König Sesostris III. Nach dem Denkstein des Oberschatzmeisters I-cher-nofret im Berliner Museum (UGAÄ 4.2), Leipzig 1904 (= Hildesheim 1964), 47-86 [Ü,K,H,F]
- J.H. Breasted, Ancient Records of Egypt, Vol. 1, Chicago 1906 (= 2001), 297-300, § 661-669 [Ü]
- G. Roeder, Aegyptische Inschriften aus den königlichen Museen zu Berlin. Bd. 1, Inschriften von der ältesten Zeit bis zum Ende der Hyksoszeit, Leipzig 1913, 169-175 und Korrekturen auf S. 209 [H]
- G. Roeder, Urkunden zur Religion des Alten Ägypten, Jena 1923, 28-30 [Ü]
- K. Sethe, Aegyptische Lesestücke zum Gebrauch im akademischen Unterricht. Texte des Mittleren Reiches, Leipzig 1924, 70-71 (Nr. 14) [H]
- K. Sethe, Erläuterungen zu den Aegyptischen Lesestücken, Leipzig 1927, 104-107 [K]
- H.G. Evers, Staat aus dem Stein: Denkmäler, Geschichte und Bedeutung der ägyptischen Plastik während des Mittleren Reichs, Bd. 2, München 1929, § 551 und Tf. III (Abb. 40) [P] (kleines Photo)
- Müller, in: MDAIK 4, 1933, Tf. 35.2 [P] (gleiches kleine Photo wie bei Evers)
- Wilson, in: ANET, 329-330 [Ü]
- W. Helck, Die Herkunft des abydenischen Osirisrituals, in: Archív Orientální 20, 1952, 72-85 [Ü, K] (72-73: Auszug Zl. G.17-24)
- H. Brunner, Altägyptische Erziehung,Wiesbaden, 1957, S. 161 (Quelle Nr. 16) [Ü] (Auszug Zl. G.5-7)
- R. Anthes, Die Berichte des Neferhotep und des Ichernofret über das Osirisfest in Abydos, in: Festschrift zum 150jährigen Bestehen des Berliner Ägyptischen Museums (Mitteilungen aus der Ägyptischen Sammlung Bd. 8), Berlin 1974, 15-49 [K]
- W.K. Simpson, The Terrace of the Great God at Abydos: The Offering chapels of Dynasties 12 and 13 (Publications of the Pennsylvania-Yale Expedition to Egypt No. 5), New Haven und Philadelphia, 1974 Tf. 1 (Nr. ANOC 1.1) [*P]
- M. Lichtheim, Ancient Egyptian literature, Bd. 1, Berkeley, Los Angeles und London, 1975, 123-125 [Ü,B]
- R.J. Leprohon, The Personnel of the Middle Kingdom Funerary Stelae, in: JARCE 15, 1978, 33-38 [K]
- D. Wildung, Sesostris und Amenemhet. Ägypten im Mittleren Reich, München, 1984, p. 137 [Ü] (Übersetzung von Zl. G.2-24)
- M. Lichtheim, Ancient Egyptian Autobiographies chiefly of the Middle Kingdom. A study an an anthology (OBO 84), Freiburg und Göttingen 1988, 98-100 (Nr. 42) [Ü,B]
- H. Buchberger, Transformation und Transformat. Sargtextstudien I (ÄA 52), Wiesbaden 1993, 350-351 [Ü,K] (Auszug Zl. G.3-8)
- R. Landgrafova, It is My Good Name that You Should Remember, Prague 2011, 204-207 (Nr. 61) [H, Ü]</bibl>
</listBibl>
</additional>
<msPart>
<msIdentifier>
<repository ref="ths:GOUD7BQ5DBCENBWBR4KFWDW5SI">Ägyptisches Museum und Papyrussammlung</repository>
<idno>1204</idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msPart>
</msDesc>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<listPrefixDef>
<prefixDef ident="tla" matchPattern="(d+)" replacementPattern="dictionary.xml#l$1"></prefixDef>
</listPrefixDef>
<listPrefixDef>
<prefixDef ident="ths" matchPattern="([wd]+)" replacementPattern="thesaurus.xml"></prefixDef>
</listPrefixDef>
<listPrefixDef>
<prefixDef ident="m" matchPattern="(w+)" replacementPattern="morphologicalFeatures.xml"></prefixDef>
</listPrefixDef>
<listPrefixDef>
<prefixDef ident="src" matchPattern="([wd]+)" replacementPattern="QDMTBLQIZZBMJGFKLESAITOSEI.xml#l$1"></prefixDef>
</listPrefixDef>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="egy-egym-Egyp-Egypreg">frühes und klassisches Mittelägyptisch-reguläre Hieroglyphenschrift
</language>
</langUsage>
<particDesc>
<listPerson type="editorial">
<person>
<persName>Renata & Peter Landgrafova & Dils</persName>
</person>
</listPerson>
</particDesc>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc status="published">
<listChange>
<change>53-5090895af6962b13dc95dcf5094c208f</change>
</listChange>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<ab>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBYBOL1KKtNefU7uqVGnun08L5k"></s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaKMJ2PRIPVZEAXFEDNIJIGVAX7Y"></s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd3SjGyaf4028lTSFmUqrUWU">(Long) live Horus Netjeri-kheperu, the perfect god 𓍹Khakaure𓍺, beloved of Osiris Khentamentiu.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaZ5JVBZCMPFFH5N4EXBJNYXVWBM">(Long) live Horus Netjeri-kheperu, the perfect god 𓍹Khakaure𓍺, beloved of Osiris Khentamentiu.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd0ohchs6xEYJsvRysNbf8Zs">Horus Netjery-kheperu, King of Upper and Lower Egypt 𓍹Khakaure𓍺, beloved of Osiris Wenennefer, given life,
Two Ladies Netjery-mesut, beloved of Osiris, the ruler,
Golden Falcon Kheperu, beloved of Osiris in the Thinite nome.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd0danzukMUXRnWLk0GYV0P8">Horus Netjery-kheperu, King of Upper and Lower Egypt Khakaure, beloved of Osiris in the Thinite nome,
Two Ladies Netjery-mesut, beloved of Osiris, Lord of the living,
Golden Falcon Kheperu, beloved of Osiris, Lord of all.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdxI5uvoa5kP8nft49rTAQ50">Hereditary noble and local prince,
royal seal-bearer, sole friend (of the king),
hereditary noble connected to the chapel of Geb,
foremost of place at the Sema-throne of Horus,
great of incense in the royal palace,
lord of prestige among the courtiers,
overseer of the treasury, Ichernofret, justified.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd875sSWYc0L4kVklRI4UQVQ">Hereditary noble and local prince,
royal seal-bearer, sole friend (of the king),
chief of secrets of the divine words (hieroglyphs),
overseer of all secret judgements,
chief of secrets of the Two Ladies (Nekhbet and Uto),
who adorns the Great-of-Magic, chief of Elkab,
overseer of the treasury, Ikhernofret, born of Zatkhonsu.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBYBOO7BExlyfkbEr73ItQ5pfIA"></s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaFBKUXGDYB5EZNPWVQ4Z6LG5O44">Behedeti, the great god.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdyJoVtpSHUyHrfGGsqTLxcw">(Osiris) Khentamentiu, Lord of Abydos, may he give life and stability like Re.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd7Dp12mQjEt2pHtvetUrDCw">Horus Netjery-kheperu, the perfect god, lord of ritual practices 𓍹Khakaure𓍺, given life for ever like Re.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdyW5wBdxj0Z7gRi32KjheP0">(Long) live Horus, Netjery-kheperu (Divine-of-transformations),
Two Ladies Netjery-mesut (Divine-of-births),
Golden Falcon Kheperu (The Transformed One),
King of Upper and Lower Egypt 𓍹Khakaure𓍺 (One-Whose-Kas-Appeared, a Re),
son of Re 𓍹Senwosret𓍺, given life for ever like Re.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd8zkVVIduEvDo1WQ9tCPPzw">A royal order for the hereditary noble and local prince, royal seal-bearer and sole friend (of the king), overseer of the two houses of gold, overseer of the two houses of silver, overseer of the treasury, Ichernofret, possessor of dignity:</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdw4xui45tkGOt3fHJWvQPfk">&quot;My Majesty commanded that you be caused to sail upstream to Abydos in the Thinite nome, in order to build a monument for (my) father Osiris Khentamenti, (and) in order to adorn [his] secret cul[tic image] with electrum, which he caused My Majesty to bring back from Nubia, in victory and triumph.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd8NX0WO7bENsmtQPQkt34lY">You will indeed do it in a truly excellent way of doing things, namely: satisfying(?) (my) father Osiris, because My Majesty sends you trusting that you will do everything to please the heart of My Majesty, (and) because it is as a pupil of My Majesty that you were brought (i.e. entrusted with the task).</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd5mIJfLCW0wPlwecErZT05Y">You have indeed grown up as a foster-child of my Majesty, the sole pupil of my palace.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdyCDr3o7YE8wglOeXKKFY9A">My Majesty appointed you as a courtier when you were (still) a youngling of 26 years.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdWaV5oSMyk8Uqi6n8Zfe3SM">My Majesty did this because I saw that you were one excellent of plans and sharp of tongue, one who came out of the womb as one knowledgeable.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdyRxip9uW0s1qCG1dztsetk">My Majesty sent you in order to do this, because My Majesty knew that there was no one who would do it all except you.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd7Yg2KjzQUJfrHasglLxI8o">Go, you, and return after you will have acted according to everything that my Majesty had ordered!&quot;</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdzJ9Q3QLZUZonoH4Hhw8CG8">I acted according to everything that his Majesty ordered, by executing perfectly all that the Lord commanded for his father Osiris Khentamenti, Lord of Abydos, great power in the Thinite nome.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd9qqo3vBWEWdu69CfIVHXb4">I acted as &quot;his beloved son&quot; to Osiris Khentamenti, I made firm [his] great [image (?)] of all eternity.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd6EYpj7F7Er6rDu1RuMGueE">I made for him a palanquin &quot;Wetjes-neferu-Khontamenti&quot; of gold and silver, lapis lazuli and amethyst (?), tamarisk (?) and Lebanese cedar;</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdzmlxvHK00NlkAIEfpQT7yA">(the images of) the gods who are in his following were set up, and their naoi were made anew.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdyWc1nDeQEcWi0B0UKWYJ24">I gave the priests of the temple [instructions] to do their tasks, and let them know the ritual of each day and the seasonal festivals.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdxpoS25ygkjOlA721JglzPY">I led the works in the neshmet barque.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd5FxeHmw1kWZt8gd5cs7Cmo">I set up a cabin.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd8AKqWOnTEMOm4QRWkr7SCw">I adorned the breast of the Lord of Abydos with lapis lazuli and turquoise, electrum and every precious stone as embellishment of the body of the god.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd2SQL6KAn0YAqUWHwW2hu6I">I clothed the god in his regalia in my office of guardian of secrets and in my function as stolist.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdWfAnNs0JEz8gUEMKhCUWQc">I was one with a clean hand in adorning the god, a sem priest clean of fingers.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd8mVSoTX3ETUnuncExCfdWk">I organised the procession of Wepwawet, when he set out to assist his father,</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd4JzsF9lmkyohosHZQ6j5vc">I repelled the attackers of the Neshemet barque, I crushed the enemies of Osiris.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdQtmxfWFOEN0qwOQJq5d1IE">I organised a great procession and followed the god on his course.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd1t06gKBQUchhHlnXFTpXZo">I caused the divine boat to sail, Thoth stearing the sailing,</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd9hhuItOn0Wbl3FG7DNjvGo">I equipped the barque Kha-em-maat of the Lord of Abydos with a cabin, and affixed his beautiful regalia, so that he might proceed to the district (?) of Peqer.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd4Enq2FoPEsokNQk7d6nWQ0">I cleared the roads of the god to his tomb at the fore of Peqer.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd5cwAr7ALk83nmj5YvrqnpA">I avenged Wenennefer on that day of the great fight,</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd4wwdwzKEklosqS4470tx1c">I crushed all his enemies on the sandban[ks] of Nedyt,</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdxT8iMkSgERorReuQoPlVbo">I caused that he entred the great barque, and it carried his beauty.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdyFArOIOX0DIoefiOBhl5m8">I gladdened the hearts of the Eastern deserts, I [caused jubi]lation in the western deserts, when they saw the beauty of the Neshmet barque as it landed at Abydos, bringing Osiris Khentiamentiu, Lord of Abydos, to his palace.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdyJI9uMKCkCrhwDk20x8vck">I followed the god to his house. He was cleansed, his place was enlarged.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdyL5fFHo009ak3bmL2Mtc38">I loosened the knot (?) in [... and he came to rest among] his [follow]ers, his retinue.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBYBOQTeECRCGEI6igKhNOxGlUo"></s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd22FENbCwkOwqwQL0GukmPk">Natron.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdxTAE0DcDE2fqX58njqWIXs">[...]</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd0odFK2C2UhxmpmirxEK65U">[... ...]</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd9IZbLDhiUMCgQjsiPLKids">His beloved brother, deputy overseer of the treasury, Ameny, possessor of dignity.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBdxlcdpivkEzkgdVQ9huiK28">Assistant of the overseer of treasury, Minhotep.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd4cXqKufO00Sg27lyPEXye4">His beloved brother, the king&#039;s acquaintance, Sasatet, possessor of dignity.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd1qR9tuNSEvJotKPx9cfYdI">His beloved son, Iykhernefret.</s>
<s xml:lang="de" corresp="src:tlaIBUBd6cH90zNm0Dfrc6oIZrqb7A">His beloved son, Sasatet.</s>
</ab>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>